[Music]
In Business Central 2025 release wave 1,
we did a almost complete makeover of the
manufacturing
reports. And uh here I will show you
what we changed also what will go away.
So that's the updated new and obsoleted
reports. And be in the beginning of this
recording if you're interested I'll tell
you a little bit about the why and the
how. If you're not interested in that,
just jump to the chapter uh directly
what is of interest to you and we'll as
always end up with some learning
resources so that you can dive in and
learn more.
So more than a year ago when we planned
many of the things that you are have
about to see um we had a vision for
manufacturing analytics simply
to completely sanitize the reporting and
analytics for this area and have it done
by
2025. And then I know it's a busy slide
but uh color coding should hopefully
help you. The first part of this is
PowerBI and colorcoded in the first part
here that you should be able to track
important relevant KPIs and scenarios in
an updated manufacturing app. The second
part is Excel and Word. So existing
reports where they where it makes sense,
we want to modernize those and uh give
them an Excel layout and maybe also a
word layout if this if we know that this
report is used a lot for printing and
we'll start deprecating these legacy RDL
reports or layouts simply because with
the other two layout options you as a
customer or user can change things in
Excel or Word. you don't need any
developer tools or anything. So that's
the reasoning behind that. The third
option or third part of the vision was
that we wanted to the the reports that
were just uh obsolete and uh we had if
we have better alternatives we'll just
deprecate the full report not the
layouts but actually getting rid of some
reports. And final part is that
everything should be discoverable and
understandable and explained in the
documentation including a new landing
page uh called manufacturing analyt
analytics. So how did we do it
practically? We we simply looked at the
usage of all manufacturing analytical
reports both how often were they used
how many customers the monthly active
tenants um and also how did how are
these reports being used are they
downloaded previewed or printed gave us
an indication of how could we uh go
about modernizing those and then based
on this data um we determined each for
each report its fate should it be
modernized? Should it be replaced or
should we just remove it? And based on
on that, we made a plan and then we
validated our assumptions with some uh
manufacturing experts from the community
just to make sure that we were on on
right track. And just behind the scenes,
this is I mean everything starts in
Excel. We know that. So this is the
planning work uh that we did on on all
these reports. for each of them we had
criteria uh usage and so on and then we
use that for just suggestions and also
uh here you can see the actuals but we
should actually see this live instead of
seeing an Excel plan so let's uh let's
go in and see some of the updated uh
reports that you have now so in
hopefully version 26.2 two, you will be
able to use updated reports for
manufacturing. Let me show you a few
examples and then we'll also demo a
few. Here's an example of a legacy
report production order statistics. The
names have been protected to uh removed
to protect the innocent. But um
basically it's a PDF and we thought
let's uh let's make this better in a
couple of ways. So, here's an modernized
version of it. It comes at this report
with two different types of layouts. A
word layout that is designed if you need
to print it and an Excel layout with
more analytical uh capabilities. Excel
layouts actually also come with a print
worksheet here in case you prefer just
to have everything in Excel and
sometimes print um print it as a
printable report. Here's another
example, the capacity task list.
Um, it is what it
is, but in a modernized world, you see
um a word layout again for print and an
Excel layout for analytics. And if you
look closely at the Word layout, it
looks actually very much the same as as
the the old layout, but with Word, you
can change things. with the RDL version
not so much subcontractor dispatch
lists. This is how it used to be and now
this is how uh it is in a modern version
again with word for print and excel for
analytics. So you can you can slice and
dice uh your subcontractor dispatch data
final and then we'll uh I'll show you a
live demo where use top level. Here is
what it looked like. And now this is one
of the examples where we know that not a
lot of customers if any print this. So
we decided just to have an Excel layout
for it where you can where you can
analyze it. But because our Excel
layouts, we always have a printable
worksheet. Um, if you need to print it,
you can just use
that. Okay, one more item, able to make
timeline. This is the old report. And
here is another example of a report that
just got a replacement um with an Excel
layout. So yeah, just one more example
of that.
So let me show you the production order
VIP also an updated report and uh let's
navigate and find that from
documentation because that was one of
the things we wanted uh you to be able
to do. So let's see production order
VIP. This is the first one. I can learn
more about the report
here so I can understand what it is but
uh all these documentation pages has try
the report. So let's just open business
central here and uh run the report uh
directly from the documentation. So when
I see the request page from production
order, I immediately see that I have
options here for layouts. So I can use
the obsoleted layout here for I can use
a word layout and I can use an Excel
layout. So, let's just choose the word
layout for the report and uh and see
what it looks
like. And here's our production order
VIP as a printable version. Let's go
back to the report and try it now with
the Excel layout instead. So, back on
the request page, I'll pick the Excel
layout instead of the Word layout and
run the report.
And here we are um production order VIP.
This is the print worksheet. But I can
also open the report in analysis mode.
Have uh all my slicers here where I can
slice and dice the data and use Excel
for Excel Excelss which is for data
analysis.
To recap the updated reports, this is uh
these are the six updated reports you
get in version 26.2, just a complete
list. So when whenever you get updated
to that version, try them out and uh
hopefully they will give you a lot more
joy in analyzing your manufacturing
data. But we didn't stop with updating
existing reports. We also wanted to add
something completely new. So here in
version 26.2, two, you get new
options. Here are some legacy reports
that are all about production cost
analysis, bomb cost share distribution,
rolled up cost shares, detail
calculation and quantity explosion of
bomb bill of
material. Instead of those four, we uh
created a new production cost shares
report in Excel. And this one is
replacing these four. So whatever you
could do of types of analysis with the
four legacy reports, you can do it
within your report. Note how many
different worksheets you have for
different roles or personas or types of
analysis. You have single level single
level top u exploded rolled up um and
rolled up top level uh rolled up
exploded. And then this these are all
the printable versions. And each of
these come uh also with a non-printable
where there's more room on the report.
So tons of tons of things to um to
explore with this new report. Um let let
let me know what you think about it when
you try it out on your
data. Similarly, we had some uh legacy
work or machine sender load reports. Um,
so work center load, machine sender
load. Um, and uh, I don't even know what
these two are because I missed the
title. Doesn't matter cuz these are all
going away and are being replaced by the
new
work/machine center load report. Again,
a report that just comes with Excel. Um,
you can see that you have uh two
printable and two analysis worksheets in
in the report. So just to wrap up that
um 26.2 you get these two new reports
production cost shares and
work/machine sender load. With all the
work we did for moni modernizing and
renewing manufacturing reports we also
need to say goodbye to some old friends.
Some of these reports have been in the
product for 30 years. So this is a
warning uh that these 711 reports are
going away in a and will will be removed
in a later version. And if you want to
know more of and follow that, let me
just show you where you can see that in
the
documentation. The first way is simply
to go and find the manufacturing
analytics
section. And then here in the table of
content, if I just scroll down, you can
see the production reports here, but
there's also a section with obsolete
reports. So they have been marked like
this in the table of content and uh
therefore you can find them here. The
second way you can see reports and other
things that are going going away in the
product being deprecated and obsoleted
is here in the deprecated features page.
So I probably the easiest way is simply
to search for deprecated features and
you'll find this. And if I choose the
2025 release wave 1 article here or part
and I just scroll down a little bit.
Let's see here. Legacy reports warning.
You get a list of the legacy reports.
Here are your manufacturing. And each of
these are links back to the
documentation page you just saw. So
these are the two options you have to uh
to find that um the warning is expressed
sorry for scrolling here. So the warning
is coming here in this uh release wave
and uh then in an like an upcoming
release wave will update this
documentation page of what um when the
report will actually be removed. If you
want to learn more about everything that
you can do within manufacturing
analytics, there's an easy way to get to
that. Let me just show you
how. The the aka link
aka.ms/bc manufacturing analytics. Let's
check this out and see what co what is
covering behind that. So this is the
landing page. If you saw the vision part
of the recording, this is the
manufacturing analytics landing page
where you get an overview of what's
possible within this area for different
personas. There's the doc the
documentation for the PowerBI
manufacturing app, the reports um and
other ways to view your manufacturing
data. So if you work with manufacturing,
I encourage you to to to take a look
here and just explore your options. So,
we made it. We are almost done. Just
wanted to wrap up with a reality
check. If you watch the vision part of
this recording in the beginning, now
um this is the status for manufacturing
analytics in this particular police
wave. We're almost done sanitizing
everything. Now in this video you
haven't looked at PowerBI and uh if you
haven't seen that video already you must
see it because with the existing reports
that you now see have been modernized in
this video and with the work that you
have we have done with uh updating the
PowerBI app for
manufacturing. There's no excuse for you
to be truly datadriven in this area. So
go out, produce some bikes, some nails,
ice cream, whatever you use
manufacturing for. But for me, the video
is over. Have a great uh rest of the
launch event. Thank you.